Finding Aid for Arthur D. Moore Papers 1916-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur D. Moore Papers 1916-1984
Moore, Arthur Dearth, 1895-
Professor of electrical engineering at University of Michigan and Ann Arbor, Michigan city councilman. Correspondence and other materials concerning professional interests and inventions, council activities, particularly urban renewal and effort to improve methods of garbage disposal and halt spread of trichinosis; and files relating to professional society, Tau Beta Pi, activities.
851959 Aa/2
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Professor Moore (donor no. 260 ) began donating his papers in May 1974. In November 1986 and May 1987, his daughter, Dr. J. C. Moore, deposited additional materials.
The collection is open for research.
Arthur Dearth Moore was born on a farm outside the town of Fairchance, Pennsylvania in January 1895. At an early age he expressed an interest in electrical phenomena. Curiosity regarding the buildup of an electrical charge in the fur of the family cat when the animal was stroked further stimulated this interest, though the experiment always terminated abruptly when he discharged the accumulated static on to the cat's nose.
At the age of six Moore announced to his family his intention to become an electrical engineer and a teacher. He attended various country schools, skipped several grades, and graduated from Uniontown High School. At age sixteen Moore entered Carnegie Tech, and he graduated in 1915 with a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering.
Moore joined Westinghouse Electric's Graduate Training Program immediately after graduation. After stints at several jobs within the program Moore became a teacher in the shop school. He remained at Westinghouse for about a year, and then joined the University of Michigan as an instructor in electrical engineering in 1916.
Moore's teaching career at the university spanned nearly forty-eight years. During this time he was promoted to assistant professor in 1920, to associate in 1928, and to full professor in 1931. He received a Master's degree in electrical engineering in 1923.
Though Moore's general area of interest was electrical engineering, his specialty was that branch of electrical engineering known as electrostatics. He defined electrostatics as "the branch of science that treats of electric phenomena associated with electric charges at rest or in motion."
In 1924 Moore was elected president of Tau Beta Pi, the national engineering honor society. He served two three-year terms, and then became fellowship director of the society for several years.
In 1940 Moore, as a Republican, successfully ran for election to the Ann Arbor city council. He was subsequently re-elected to eight consecutive terms and served on council until 1957. In 1955 he was elected council president, and in that position served as acting mayor on several occasions.
Moore's two most significant contributions while a member of the council were in the areas of sanitation, where he was successful in having his proposals implemented, and urban renewal, where he was not. In the area of sanitation, Moore pushed for city-wide refuse collection and for the establishment of a sanitary landfill, hoping to end the practice of feeding the city's garbage to hogs. Several diseases, most notably trichinosis, were spread as a result of this practice. In conjunction with this effort, Moore also helped organize and served as vice-president of the First and Second National Conferences on Trichinosis in 1952 and 1954 respectively.
Moore was not as successful with his urban renewal efforts. He proposed a comprehensive plan for the so-called north central area, which was the area in the city of Ann Arbor bounded by Catherine and Ann Streets and Miller Avenue on the south; Ashley Street on the west; Division Street on the east; and Depot Street to the north. Though the proposal was endorsed by groups such as the Ann Arbor League of Women Voters, Moore's plans were not implemented.
In 1941, with World War II underway and the possibility of American entry into the conflict growing more likely, Moore was asked to become a personnel recruiter for the Naval Ordnance Laboratory. It was felt that his connections with many scientists and engineers through Tau Beta Pi and other professional organizations would be valuable in helping to fill staff positions in that organization. In the next several months Moore recruited and hired over 150 men.
Moore gained a reputation in the field of electrostatics as a great inventor. Some of his more noteworthy inventions included the hydrocal, a hydraulic analog used to simulate and measure heat transients; the dirod, a generator which proved to be both reliable and rugged, and which served as a model for many high school science fair projects; and(although not an original invention but rather a continuation of work dropped by Professor Hele-Shaw at Oxford in the early twentieth century) fluid mapping devices of various kinds. These fluid mappers showed a visual portrayal of fluid flow of potential fields. Companies and individuals applied these fluid mapping techniques to solve engineering problems in areas such as underground gas recovery and storage and canal seepage.
While Moore received emeritus status from the University of Michigan at the end of the fall semester in 1963, his career in electrostatics did not slow down. In 1964, with a grant from Lapp Insulator and Union Carbide, Moore set out on a; lecture-demonstration tour of the western United States. He demonstrated his electrostatics equipment to thousands of engineers, students and other interested onlookers over the next seventeen years. Moore's travels during this period also took him to England, Scotland, Denmark, and Sweden, as he covered nearly 150,000 miles by air and by automobile to give his demonstrations.
During retirement Moore published several works on electrostatics, supplementing his earlier contributions of published articles and an unpublished monograph, "Comparative Animal Energy." In 1968 his book Electrostatics was published. This was an introductory text, part of Doubleday's Science Study Series, and eventually translations of the book were printed in Italian, German, and Japanese. Another book, Invention, Creativity, and Discover y followed in 1969 as part of the same series. Also, Moore approached John Wiley and Sons, publishers with an idea for a professional book on electrostatics. This was to be the first book of its kind on the subject. Moore recruited a team of seventeen experts in the field to write the chapters of the book, and he served as editor. The book, Electrostatics, was published in 1973.
The Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers did not include electrostatics as a recognized branch of the electrical engineering field. For this reason, as well as what Moore perceived to be an attitude of neglect toward the field of electrostatics in general, he founded on August 17, 1970 the Electrostatics Society of America. The society's first conference, sponsored by the American Meteorological Society, was held in Albany in 1971.
When not busy with his electrostatics pursuits Arthur Moore enjoyed billiards, juggling, and camping. A 1947 demonstration of billiards at the Michigan Union, organized by Moore and-featuring Willie Hoppe and Charles Peterson, played to a packed house. Two months out of each year were spent at the family cabin at Algoma Mills, Ontario, about halfway between Sudbury and Sault St. Marie. This tradition was carried on for over forty years. Moore maintained his combination office/laboratory in the university's electrical and computer engineering department until the mid-1980s.
The papers of Arthur Dearth Moore document his career teacher and researcher at the University of Michigan, pioneering work in the field of electrostatics, activities in professional organizations, and his service on the Ann Arbor City Council. The papers have been divided into the following groups of material: Biographical; Correspondence; Tau Beta Pi; Naval Ordnance Laboratory; Organizations; Instructional Materials; Published Works; Unpublished Works; Hydrocal; Electrostatics Society of America; Reference Files-Electrostatics; Ann Arbor City Council; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Electrostatics.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Inventions.; Moore, Arthur Dearth, 1895-; Refuse and refuse disposal.; Tau Beta Pi.; Trichinosis.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Urban renewal.; Science Research Club (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Billiards.; Electrostatics.; Exhibitions.; Hawaii.; Machine shops.; Moore, Arthur Dearth, 1895-; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors
Krueger, Albert.
Contributors: Visual Materials
Gundlach, Robert.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical
  Biographical contains miscellaneous sources of material, some written by Moore himself.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series has been divided into four subseries, three by time period (and then alphabetically) and one for Moore's correspondence with Albert Krueger. Much of the 1927-1940 correspondence pertains to Moore's role as professor of electrical engineering at the University of Michigan, and covers a wide variety of topics in electrical engineering and teaching. The 1944-1964 correspondence focuses largely on biology and his research for an unpublished study entitled, "Comparative Animal Energy." The 1965-1984 correspondence consists largely of material describing Moore's retirement activities, particularly his traveling and electrostatics lectures and demonstrations. The Albert Krueger subseries covers the period, 1972-1981, and consists of correspondence with Krueger, a medical doctor at the University of California-Berkeley. Krueger's main area of interest involved the biological effects of air ionization.
  - 1927-1940
    - A-W, 24 folders (Box 1)
      (include individual folders for Calvert, Dudley, Robertson, Rowley, and Seelig)
  - 1944-1964
    - A-W, 22 folders (Box 1)
      (include individual folders for Bogert, Colbert, Macmillan, and Rowan)
  - 1965-1984
    - A (Box 1)
    - B, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Blanchard (Box 1)
    - C, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Conrad, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - D, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Dunn, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - E, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - F, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - G, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Gundlach, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - H, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Harris (Box 2)
    - I (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - K, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Kalbach, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Kraus (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - M, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Manning, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Maurer (Box 2)
    - Masuda (Box 2)
    - Mayes (Box 2)
    - Meiner (Box 2)
    - Morris (Box 2)
    - Mc, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - N (Box 2)
    - O (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - Pers (Box 3)
    - Platt (Box 3)
    - Pollard (Box 3)
    - Pounder, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - R (Box 3)
    - Richards (Box 3)
    - Robin (Box 3)
    - Robinson (Box 3)
    - Rosenfeld (Box 3)
    - Rotelli (Box 3)
    - S, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Saper (Box 3)
    - Singleton, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - Tassicker (Box 3)
    - Teal (Box 3)
    - Tribus (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - V (Box 3)
    - W, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Walker (Box 3)
    - Walkup (Box 3)
    - Wallach (Box 3)
    - Watlington (Box 3)
    - Wedemeyer (Box 3)
    - Y (Box 3)
    - Z (Box 3)
  - Albert Krueger correspondence
    - 1972-1978, 14 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979-June 1981, 11 folders (Box 4)
- Tau Beta Pi 1926-1955
  Tau Beta Pi, 1926-1955, contains that society's constitution and bylaws, minutes and memoranda of conventions, correspondence, budget sheets, applications, reports on the progress of student members and of various universities, and surveys on engineering education methods and war attitudes.
  - Applications 1932-1934 (Box 4)
  - Budget sheets 1926-1931 (Box 4)
  - Constitution and bylaws 1927, 1932, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Conventions-minutes and memoranda 1931-1934, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1927-1955, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports--students 1932-1933 (Box 4)
  - Reports--universities 1931 (Box 4)
  - Survey of engineering education methods 1936 (Box 4)
  - War attitudes survey 1941, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Naval Ordnance Laboratory 1941
  The Naval Ordnance Laboratory series consists of one folder of correspondence and memoranda pertaining to Moore's work as a personnel recruiter for that organization in 1941.
  - Correspondence and memoranda 1941 (Box 4)
- Organizations 1916-1944
  Organizations, 1916-1944, contains a variety of materials on various organizations: the Association of College Honor Societies, of which Moore served as president; the Junior Research Club, where he served as vice president; the Science Research Club; and the University Club, where he again served as president for a time.
  - Association of College Honor Societies 1925-1939, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Junior Research Club 1930-1944, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Science Research Club
    - Science Vignettes
      - #1-48 1976-1983 (with index) (Box 4)
      - Unindexed 1978-1985 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous materials 1978-1985 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1978-1998 (Box 4)
  - University Club 1916-1942 (Box 4)
- Instructional Materials 1920s, 1940s, 1950s
  Instructional Materials has been divided into two subseries, 1920s and 1940s-1950s, both alphabetically arranged. A variety of subjects are included, among them materials pertaining to electrical and mechanical design schools, extension courses, convection, direct current motor designs, dry cells, heat diffusion, meters, magnets, radiation, and transient problems.
  - 1920s
    - Electrical design school (Box 4)
    - Extension courses (Box 4)
    - Flux notes, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Mechanical design school (Box 5)
    - Solenoid and starting motor-automobile (Box 5)
    - Syllabus-Electrical Engineering 5 (Box 5)
    - Teaching and learning (Box 5)
  - 1940s 1950s
    - Convection (Box 5)
    - Direct current motor design (Box 5)
    - Dry cells (Box 5)
    - Duncan Watt-Hour Meter (Box 5)
    - Heat diffusion (Box 5)
    - Horizontal cylinder in air (Box 5)
    - Interpolation (Box 5)
    - Lincoln Meter (Box 5)
    - Magnetic bridge (Box 5)
    - Magnets (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Motor design (Box 5)
    - Radiation (Box 5)
    - Reactance (Box 5)
    - Series lockout magnet (Box 5)
    - Thermometers (Box 5)
    - Three dimensional field maps (Box 5)
    - Transformer points (Box 5)
    - Transient problems, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Published Works 1917-1982
  Published Works, 1917-1982, contains a variety of published articles and monographs, all, with the exception of a monograph published by the Hoover Steel Ball Company of Ann Arbor, written by Moore. Two of the monographs, Electrostatics and Invention, Creativity, and Discovery were marketed as regular trade books.
  - Evolution of the Steel Ball Industry, 1917 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1926-1950 (Box 5)
  - Hydrocal 1936 (Box 5)
  - Heat Transfer Notes for Electrical Engineering, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Eddy Currents in Disks; Driving and Damping Forces and Torques 1946 (Box 5)
  - Electrospherics and Magnetospherics 1959, 1962 (Box 5)
  - "The Magic Carpet: Water-Floated Magnetized Balls Form Standing Waves When Driven by A-C Magnetic Field," 1964 (Box 5)
  - Electrostatics, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Invention, Creativity, and Discovery, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Henry Rowland 1982 (Box 5)
- Unpublished Works 1947, 1977
  The Unpublished Works series contains texts of two items: "Comparative Animal Energy" (1947), and "Spheres and Other Round Things" (1977) as well as various material on these works.
  - Comparative Animal Energy 1947, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Spheres and Other Round Things 1977, 4 folders (Box 5)
- Hydrocal circa 1934-1954
  The Hydrocal series, 1934-1954, contains material relating to Moore's invention that aided in the measurement of heat transfer of various surfaces. It includes a blueprint, calibrations, correspondence and memoranda,. a journal, descriptions of operations, and research notes.
  - Blueprint (Box 5)
  - Calibrations, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda 1934-1954 (Box 5)
  - Journal 1948-1949 (Box 5)
  - Operations (Box 5)
  - Research notes, 5 folders (Box 6)
- Electrostatics Society Of America 1969-1982
  Electrostatics Society of America, 1969-1980, contains, that organization's constitution and history, conference material, correspondence, business informal technical sessions material, membership lists, council actions, executive council meeting minutes, and Small Ion Committee materials.
  - Business Informal Technical Sessions 1974, 1976, 1978, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Conferences
    - 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1975 (Box 6)
    - 1977, 1979, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Constitution and history (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1969-1982 (Box 6)
  - Council action 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - Electrostatics Research Center 1980 (Box 6)
  - Executive Council 1974 (Box 6)
  - Membership 1971, 1973, 1978-1980 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Small Ion Committee 1979 (Box 6)
- Reference Files-Electrostatics circa 1930s-1980s
  Reference Files - Electrostatics, ca. 1930s-1980s, has been divided into two subseries of materials, applications and atmospheric. Both subseries are alphabetically arranged, with the applications files containing the far greater amount of material. Topics covered under applications include air pollution control, dirod, electrets, fluid mappers, generators hazards of electrostatics, heat transfer, imaging, Kirilian photography, marine oil tankers, miscellaneous, non-impact printing, plants, and static. The atmospheric files contains a bibliography, general material, and materials relating to the ionosphere, lightning, snow, and tornadoes.
  - Applications
    - Air pollution control, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Autopilots (Box 6)
    - Corona motor (Box 6)
    - Dirod
      - Accessories (Box 6)
      - Baby Dirod (Box 6)
      - Characteristics (Box 6)
      - Designs (Box 6)
      - Dirod I (Box 6)
      - Dirod II (Box 6)
      - Dirod Junior (Box 6)
      - Dirod VII (Box 6)
      - Manual (Box 6)
      - Notes (Box 6)
      - Performance (Box 6)
    - Dry coatings (Box 6)
    - Earphones and speakers (Box 6)
    - Electrets, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Electrofax based papers (Box 6)
    - Electrostatics--definition (Box 6)
    - Electrostatics lecture demonstration (Box 6)
    - Fiber fractionation (Box 6)
    - Fluidization (Box 6)
    - Fluid mappers (Box 6)
    - Future of electrostatics (Box 6)
    - Generators, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Gyroscope (Box 6)
    - Hazards of electrostatics (Box 6)
    - Heat transfer (Box 7)
    - Imaging (Box 7)
    - Kirilian photography (Box 7)
    - Levitation (Box 7)
    - Marine-oil tankers, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Non-impact printing, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Non-uniform fields (Box 7)
    - Plants (Box 7)
    - Rattleback (Box 7)
    - Static (Box 7)
    - Surgery (Box 7)
    - Wet coatings (Box 7)
  - Atmospheric
    - Bibliography (Box 7)
    - General (Box 7)
    - Ionosphere (Box 7)
    - Lightning, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Snow (Box 8)
    - Tornadoes (Box 8)
- Ann Arbor City Council 1941-1958
  The Ann Arbor City Council series, 1941-1958, contains a correspondence file as well as material relating to housing, sanitation, and urban renewal.
  - Correspondence and memoranda 1941-1956 (Box 8)
  - Housing 1942-1949 (Box 8)
  - Sanitation 1941-1956
    - Clippings 1952-1953 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1941-1956, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - First National Conference on Trichinosis 1952 (Box 8)
    - Second National Conference on Trichinosis 1954 (Box 8)
  - Urban Renewal 1950-1958
    - Clippings
      - 1950, 1955 (Box 8)
      - 1956 (Box 8)
      - 1958, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1955-1958, 4 folders (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes a variety of information. A folder titled "Billiards" contains a 1942 paper written by Moore entitled "Mechanics of Billiards, and Analysis of Willie Hoppe's Stroke." A clippings file, ca. 1940-1974, contains newspaper and other clippings focusing on various aspects of Moore's life. In addition, there are six folders of photographs and a videocassette of Moore being interviewed.
  - Billiards 1942 Mechanics of Billiards, and Analysis of Willie Hoppe's Stroke, 1942 (Box 8)
  - Clippings 1940-1974 (Box 8)
  - Anne Benninghoff collected materials (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 6 folders (Box 8)
    Photographs of various electrostatics equipment; also photos of Moore at meetings and with professional groups; and photos of billiards demonstration. demonstration
  - Videocassette produced by the Electrostatics Society of America and entitled "A.D. Moore Remembered (1895-1989).", 1992
    The videocassette produced in 1992 consists of a conversation with Moore conducted by Bob Gundlach, Senior Research Fellow at Xerox, in 1977 in which Moore discusses and demonstrates through experiments his interest in electrostatics and its application to xerography.
    - A.D. Moore Remembered, interviewed by Bob Gundlach (Box 8)
    - University of Michigan College of Engineering Electrostatics lecture and demonstration, June 8, 1983, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 8)